Guide to the Wider City Parish Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
Wider City Parish Records
1950-1987
RG 87
Yale University Divinity School Library
5
(11 boxes)
These archives document the work of a nondenominational Christian social ministry agency during three decades of rapid urban change and upheaval in New Haven. The Wider City Parish was an inner-city Christian social ministry organization in New Haven, Connecticut, which existed from the early 1950s to the mid 1980s. Its executive director was Robert Forsberg, a graduate of the Yale Divinity School.
Wider City Parish
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Wider City Parish
Biographical / Historical
The Wider City Parish began in 1952 as the Oak Street Christian Parish, located in the Oak Street area of New Haven. When urban renewal brought a highway through this area, the Parish relocated to Ashmun Street, changed its name, and refocused its activities on projects and projects in various areas of New Haven, including the Rockview-Brookside housing project, the Elm Haven and other downtown housing projects, the Howard Avenue and Grand Avenue areas, as wellas the margins of the Oak Street area. Supported by the New Haven Council of Churches, the Wider City Parish sought to inform the congregations of New Haven about inner city problems, and to coordinate support for a variety of programs. The staff of the Parish was always small, and usually included a number of part-time Yale Divinity School students. Programs and projects included summer programs for children, family counseling, work among Puerto Rican immigrants, and advocate work in the areas of housing, young offenders in court, adult education, etc.
Scope and Contents
The records provide valuable documentation of a locally operated and supported nondenominational Christian social service agency during a period of rapid urban change and upheaval in New Haven. Urban problems of housing, education, crime, racism, and immigration were addressed by the Parish, led by Yale Divinity School graduate Robert Forsberg.
Series I, Legal Documents, traces the formation of the Oak Street Christian Parish and its change of name to the Wider City Parish. The reports and minutes of Series II, provide documentation of the development of the organization, its operations, and its changing program emphases. The Files of Robert Forsberg, Executive Director, in Series III complement the more systematic records of Series II, and illustrate the processes of networking and support-gathering that sustained the Wider City Parish.
The Programs and Projects of Series IV are those sponsored by the Wider City Parish, or in which they were partners with other organizations. Most substantial of these programs were summer programs for children, including the Friendly Town program that paired inner-city children with suburban families, and community support programs, including a library, at the Elm Haven housing project. Documentation of the organization in New Haven for the 1963 March on Washington, and interactions with the New Haven grassroots group, the Union of Indigent People, provide vivid illustration of the role of a Christian service agency in the struggle to improve urban conditions.
The Publications of Series V include Wider City Parish newsletters dating from1952 to 1987, which provide an excellent overview of the program emphases of the Parish and its efforts to garner support from city and suburban congregations in the New Haven area. Many of the photographs in Series VI were used in its publications. Series VII, Collected Material and Related Organizations, documents the Wider City Parish's place in the wider network of social service agencies and programs. There is some overlap between this series and Series III and IV, but, in general, the documentation of Series VII is of programs in which the Wider City Parish was not a direct participant. The Financial Records of Series VIII, which conclude the record group, add yet another piece to the documentation of the Wider City Parish's three decades of service in New Haven.
Arrangement
I. Legal Documents, 1952-1975
II. Committees and Reports, 1952-1986, n.d.
III. Files of Robert Forsberg, Executive Director, 1964-1980
IV. Programs and Projects, 1951-1980, n.d.
V. Publications, 1952-1987
VI. Photographs, n.d.
VII. Collected Material and Related Organizations, 1959-1986, n.d.
VIII. Financial Records, 1954-1985, n.d.
City missions -- United States -- History -- 20th Century; Wider City Parish
- Legal Documents, 1952-1975; Series I
  - Articles of Association and By-Laws, 1952-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Dixwell Legal Rights, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - IRS Documents, 1953-1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous Legal Material, 1955-1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Committees and Reports, 1952-1986, n.d.; Series II
  - Annual Meeting Reports, 1957-1982,n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5-24)
  - Board of Directors: Minutes, 1957-1981 (Box 2, Folder 25-43)
  - Board of Directors: Reports, 1952-1966 (Box 2, Folder 44-58)
  - Board of Directors: Reports, 1967-1986 (Box 3, Folder 59-74)
  - Executive Committee: Minutes, 1972, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Miscellaneous Committees, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Steering Committee, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Steering Committee, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 78)
- Files of Robert Forsberg, Executive Director, 1964-1980; Series III
  - Correspondence and program material, 1964-1980 (Box 4, Folder 79-94)
- Programs and Projects, 1951-1980, n.d; Series IV
  - After School Christian Education, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 95)
  - Black Community Enabler, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 96)
  - Bonding Program, 1973-1977 (Box 4, Folder 97)
  - Board for Urban Ministry, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 98)
  - Christmas Toy Sales, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 99)
  - Church and Public Education, 1970-1972 (Box 5, Folder 100)
  - Citizens' Commission, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 101)
  - Citizens for Safety, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 102)
  - City Missionary Alliance, 1970-1983 (Box 5, Folder 103)
  - Committee Renewal Team, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 107)
  - Dixwell Neighborhood Council, 1965-1972 (Box 5, Folder 109)
  - Dixwell pre-school training, 1967-1969 (Box 5, Folder 110)
  - East Haven Protestant Parish, 1954-1955 (Box 5, Folder 111)
  - Elm Haven Community Council, 1957-1978 (Box 6, Folder 112)
  - Elm Haven Enlightenment Workshop, 1961-1968 (Box 6, Folder 113)
  - Elm Haven Library Project, 1965-1977 (Box 6, Folder 114-115)
  - Elm Haven Parish Council, 1966-1968 (Box 6, Folder 116)
  - Friendly Town Program, 1967-1968 (Box 6, Folder 117-118)
  - Friends of the WCP, 1960-1963 (Box 6, Folder 119)
  - Group Ministry, 1960-1968 (Box 6, Folder 120)
  - Inter-Parish Staff Conference, 1952-1960 (Box 7, Folder 121)
  - Job Descriptions, 1968-1974 (Box 7, Folder 122)
  - Layman's Conference, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 123)
  - LEAP, 1964-1967 (Box 7, Folder 124)
  - LINK, 1963-1967 (Box 7, Folder 125)
  - March on Washington, 1963 (Box 7, Folder 126)
  - Ministry of Laity, 1961-1963 (Box 8, Folder 127)
  - Model Cities Project, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 129)
  - Narcotics Program, 1964-1968 (Box 8, Folder 130)
  - National Commission on Technology, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 131)
  - New Haven Situation, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 132)
  - Oak Street Parish: Historical essays, 1951, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 133)
  - Oak Street Parish: Documents, 1950-1960 (Box 8, Folder 134-135)
  - Oak Street Community House, 1954 (Box 9, Folder 136)
  - Office Correspondence, 1966-1968 (Box 9, Folder 137)
  - Office Correspondence, 1973-1979 (Box 8, Folder 128)
  - Peace Education, 1980 (Box 9, Folder 138)
  - Prison Program, 1965-1966 (Box 9, Folder 139)
  - Public Education Ministry Proposals, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 140)
  - Puerto Rican Community Project, 1957-1958 (Box 9, Folder 141)
  - Requests for Work, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 142)
  - Rockview-Brookside Advisory Committee, 1962-1965 (Box 9, Folder 143)
  - Senior Citizens' Association, 1962-1964 (Box 9, Folder 144)
  - Student Jobs, 1961-1962 (Box 9, Folder 145)
  - Summer Program, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 147)
  - Summer Program, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 148)
  - Summer Program, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 149)
  - Summer Program, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 150)
  - Summer Program, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 151)
  - Summer Program, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 152)
  - Teenage Outing Clubs, 1964-1967 (Box 9, Folder 153)
  - Union of Indigent People, 1965-1972 (Box 9, Folder 154)
  - WCP Goals and Objectives (Box 9, Folder 155)
  - WCP MID-Winter Retreat, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 156)
  - WCP Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 157)
  - WCP Third Birthday Party, 1960 (Box 10, Folder 158)
  - Yale-New Haven Hospital Connector Parking, 1969 (Box 10, Folder 159)
  - Youth March for Integrated Schools, 1959 (Box 10, Folder 160)
- Publications, 1952-1987; Series V
  - Request for Publications, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 169)
  - WCP News Letter, 1952-1987 (Box 10, Folder 170-174)
- Photographs, n.d.; Series VI
  - Photographs, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 179)
- Collected Material and Related Organizations, 1959-1986, n.d; Series VII
  - Black People in American Life: Bibliography, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 161)
  - Board of National Missions, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 162)
  - Cleveland Inner City Protestant Parish, 1959-1962 (Box 5, Folder 104-106)
  - Connecticut Valley Presbytery, 1978-1980 (Box 5, Folder 108)
  - Dwight Area Human Service Agencies, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 163)
  - Dwight Hall Personnel, 1960-1961 (Box 10, Folder 164)
  - Hope and Summerfield Methodist Churches, 1965 (Box 10, Folder 165)
  - Leadership of New Haven, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 166)
  - J.P. Steven's Boycott, 1977-1978 (Box 10, Folder 167)
  - Yale Hope Mission, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 168)
- Financial Records, 1954-1985, n.d.; Series VIII
  - Audit Reports, 1969-1977 (Box 10, Folder 175)
  - Cooperative Parish Sharing, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 176)
  - Financial Budgets, 1954-1985 (Box 10, Folder 177)
  - Financial Contributions, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 178)